[Music]
How to buy the best maps in 2025. You're
doing it wrong. You're still using this
to navigate life. Embarrassing.
[Music]
I'm so bored right now and I truly hate
the way it feels. You're probably bored,
too. You clicked on this video trying to
feel less bored and all you've got is a
guy scrolling on his phone alone in a
room. Here. Let me see if I can help
with
that. Is this
better? Good. It's not just you and me.
It's
everyone. Boredom is on the rise. Even
at a time when we're in the golden age
of content, boredom isn't simple. It's
not trivial. It's not benign. It's
actually a painful emotion that quietly
haunts our sense of meaning and purpose.
It's more like pain or disgust. We've
been going deep on this. There's a lot
of great new science. My producer, Alex,
read like five books on the topic. In
all of this literature, I am starting to
see a clear story that explains why all
of us are more bored than ever. But I'm
also seeing something that I didn't
expect, something that's quietly hidden
within the feeling of boredom. how this
really unpleasant feeling, boredom,
might actually be key to living a more
purposeful, creative
life. Your life is like a road trip.
Stick with me while I build this analogy
because it's actually really useful for
understanding the real meaning of
boredom. It's a road trip in the dark.
In this analogy, the most important
parts are first off your headlights.
This is your attention, your ability to
pay attention and what you pay attention
to. And the second most important part
is this fuel tank. We're going to look
at this a lot. This represents your
sense of meaning and purpose. It helps
motivate you, pushes you along the
journey of your life. Attention and
meaning are vital for how humans
navigate their lives, how they make
decisions on where to go with the
constraints of their everyday
experience. These determine the route
that you take on this road trip. So,
you're going along your life. You're
taking turns. You're making decisions on
how to spend your time. You spend time
with friends. You pay attention to this
and look, your tank is filling up with
meaning and purpose. For a lot of us,
friendship is fuel. You go for a walk,
maybe in nature, you listen to music.
That is meaningful to you. Maybe you
watch a good movie. You shine your
attention on that and that is actually
pretty fulfilling. But life is heavy and
hard. And sometimes your fuel runs out.
Your attention fractures or fades. And
then this
happens. Lights out. This is boredom.
the state where your sense of purpose
and meaning is on empty and consequently
you don't really have the ability to
muster the energy to pay attention to
something that would change the
situation. Real quick before we go on,
have you noticed that one way you might
cure your boredom is email? Knocking out
a few emails makes you feel productive,
doesn't take that much work sometimes,
but if you look closely, you might note
that a lot of the emails you're knocking
out are actually junk. Like they
shouldn't have been there. You don't
want them there. You never signed up for
them. This same thing extends to
roocalls and all of those text messages
you get and even junk mail being sent to
your house. It's sort of a constant
low-level buzz and one that I kind of
hate. I'm telling you all this cuz it
has to do with our sponsor today,
Incogn.
Incogn. These are companies who make a
lot of money off of collecting your
information, your address, your shopping
habits, your birthday, your court
records, and selling it to anyone
willing to pay. marketers, credit
agencies, insurance companies, you name
it. I actually heard about
incogn, I gave them permission to act on
my behalf and then they went out to
these data brokers and say to them in
some legal language, "Hey, take Johnny
off your lists and it has worked
hundreds of times actually automatically
without me having to do anything. I
actually just get to sit back and look
at this fancy looking dashboard, see the
status of all of the requests that have
been made and the ones that have been
successful, which at this point there's
like hundreds of them. In fact, let me
do a little update right now. Incogn
what is my current number of? Dude, 744
total requests to these data brokers.
And of those, 612 have been completed.
That's very satisfying. 132 are in
progress. Man, this is great. Just this
month, there have been more than 10. Get
to see all of this. It's very
satisfying. They just launched this
unlimited plan which now allows you to
request removal from any site, including
those creepy people search sites that
post your info online for anyone to see.
So, if you want to try this out, go to
incognito.com/jny Harris. Clicking that
link helps support this channel. If you
use the code Johnny Harris at checkout,
you get 60% off the annual plan. I do
the annual plan because, like I said,
like every month there are more lists
that I get added to and Incogn scans
them and takes me off of them. So, thank
you Incogn for sponsoring today's video,
for allowing us to do this work. With
that, let's dive back into why we are so
bored. The most surprising thing that
I've learned so far while researching
this is that boredom is not this
trivial, mundane feeling. It's actually
a pretty strong emotional experience and
it kind of sucks. I define boredom as
meaning withdrawal, as a sense of
discomfort, telling you that your need
for personal meaning is not being met.
Your brain's way of telling you you need
to change what you're doing because what
you're doing is unsatisfying. You find
it hard to focus. And that feeling of
like, I can't do anything about this. I
don't have any, you know, agency here or
what's the meaning of all of this?
You're just kind of stuck there. I'd say
that the experience of boredom is an
experience of unfreedom, an experience
of being trapped in the present without
meaning. Time seems to slow. You're in a
situation where I don't care about this.
This really doesn't stimulate me in in
in any way. Toltoy described boredom as
like a desire of desires. I also
remember a friend of mine. He worked
with the postal services when we were
students and his job was to take
mailbags and turn them inside out to see
if there was uh any letters remaining in
there. And one day he told me yesterday
at work I just started weeping. I mean
this was the myth of Seisphus the
eternal recurrence of the same. There is
no end to it. There will there would
always be another mailbag coming in that
would have to be turned inside out. No
progression, just the same over and over
again. And he started weeping at work,
though being a good Protestant, he
continued to turn mailbags inside out
while he was
weeping. For me, this happens usually on
a Saturday at like 300 p.m. This is when
my kids are occupied playing with
friends or playing Nintendo or whatever.
I have time. I usually don't have time,
but Saturday at 3 p.m. I have precious
free time that I don't get during the
week. And I have all this stuff that I
want to do, but then this emotion just
hits me. This feeling that I don't
really want to do anything. Like, I
can't really muster the motivation to do
any of it. And suddenly things get
really dark for me. I start to question
everything. I start to question my life
choices. I'm angry at myself for not
doing things that I know some part of me
wants to do. I'm wondering if I've made
the right life choices. So, I know this
feeling well, but before reporting the
story, I never called it boredom. I kind
of thought it was like some flash of
depression or restlessness or maybe it
was my ADD or something. Boredom always
just felt like this thing that like
there's nothing to do and so I'm bored.
But that's actually not what's happening
here. Many would call it an emotional
state that has cognitive and
physiological coralates. Bottom is the
feeling of thinking. It's an affective
response to underutilization of our
capacities of our cognitive skills.
Right? So when you're bored, you're
having that affective reaction to the
fact that you're not using your brain as
well as you could be. So yeah, boredom
is an emotion and it's very
uncomfortable. But luckily, I've got a
very quick little medicine that is in my
pocket at all times. Is not in my pocket
right now. Uh-oh. Where's my little
medicine? It's a small computer device
that was probably made in China or
India. And it's got software on it that
numbs my boredom. Some people call it a
phone, but a phone is a thing that was
invented like a 100 years ago where
people talk to each other. Where is
Where is it? Where does my phone? Oh,
here she is. She was here the whole
time. Ah, my precious. Now, the latest
nuclear missile test conducted just
hours. About 3 years ago, I was cooking
rice to my test.
Oh man, I love Tik Tok and all short
form video that I consume to cure my
boredom. And and to be clear, this video
will critique all of this and tell us
about how the brain is kind of getting
messed up with some of the stuff, but
boy, it's fun while it lasts. Anyway,
this device is very useful for curing my
boredom, and I use it Saturdays at 3:00
p.m. when I'm feeling bored. And yes,
later I will show you the studies that
unpack boredom and phone use. But for
now, I was actually curious if other
people experience this the way I do
because it's a deeply personal and
emotional experience. And so I asked my
team. So I usually get bored when I get
home from work and I've done all the
things that I wanted to do like eat
dinner, hang out with friends, go to the
gym, do a hobby, and there's still time
left over somehow. I get this really
uncomfortable feeling, which is boredom.
That's this like existential gut punch.
and I think about what am I doing with
my life and I want to crawl out of my
own skin. Typically I will numb it with
Tik Tok or playing video games. But
sometimes I will sit in it, sit in the
discomfort and think about my life, but
that is a lot more work and exhausting.
Ironically though, I I have noticed that
I find my phone to be a sort of boring
replacement for the boredom. there's
this sort of instant gratification with
social media that feels like it's the
addictive version of boredom and uh yeah
that is kind of
scary. Okay, before we get back to the
car analogy, which is very good and very
useful, I promise. I want to explain
what I've learned about why. Why does
boredom even exist inside of our brains?
And it turns out that it's actually a
very natural biological signal that we
developed a long time ago. What's
happening when we're bored is a bunch of
brain regions are coming together to
tell us that we need to do something
different with our situation. One of the
defining traits of human beings is that
we are restless. We need purpose and
meaning to fuel our actions. And this
has been one way that humans have been
pushed to create and change their
natural situation. Not just for more
resources like all animals do, but also
in search of meaning. We're these
self-aware apes who are able to tell
stories of meaning and purpose to each
other. And we ourselves are kind of
characters in our own story. It's a
major reason why humans have been able
to cooperate in large numbers with each
other. Looking towards stories like
corporations or religions or countries.
All of these are meaningful stories that
bind us together to cooperate and change
our situation. So a lot of experts now
think that boredom is this emotional cue
that is pushing us to do something
different with our lives to deliver on
that need for meaning. But boredom today
is pretty different. In fact, in the old
days, most people didn't have time to
get bored. It's typical for traditional
societies that you don't have to spend a
lot of time thinking about what to care
about because it's already defined for
you. Let's do one of my favorite things
and rewind and see what my little road
trip analogy would have looked like if I
lived 500 years ago. So, I'm a farmer.
Most of us would have been farmers, FYI.
And I spend most of my time working on
the farm because if I don't, my family
and I will die. So, my attention is
locked into kind of one highstakes
activity that defines my life. Let's
look down at my meaning and purpose fuel
tank. Oh, wo, it's doing great. And
look, you can see why. Here on the farm,
my sense of purpose and meaning flows in
abundance from my family, my belonging
to a community in which I was born that
has well-defined culture and rituals
that my ancestors have been doing for
thousands of years. And perhaps most of
all, I have a clear existential story in
the form of religion. This makes death
and suffering not so bad, and it fills
me with a bigger purpose. This stuff is
like rocket fuel for our sense of
meaning and belonging and purpose. Now,
it doesn't mean life was easy. Not at
all. But it does mean that we didn't get
bored. We didn't have time to get bored
and we didn't have any lack of meaning
and purpose. It was all kind of
automated for us by our culture. I think
that the experience of boredom was
certainly there in traditional or
preodern societies, but it really gains
traction in modernity. The word has has
has maybe not been around as long as we
might imagine, but that doesn't mean
that the concept and the experience and
the feeling isn't ancient. Boredom was
more of a privilege for uh those who
were the royal courts, the clergy and so
on. Rich aristocrats were the rare human
beings that had time on their hands. The
other group were monks who had quite a
bit of time before the rest of us. And
in fact, they had a word to describe
this feeling of boredom. Called it
acadia, a lack of motivation to fulfill
your purpose, or in this case, your
duties to God. Christians would frame
this early concept of boredom as a
dangerous sin that could kill your
faith. They would nickname it the
noonday demon, the most dangerous of all
the demons because from boredom stemmed
many other sinful behaviors and they
were kind of on to something as we will
see in the scientific literature very
soon. French monks updated the
interpretation to a desire to escape the
present, a tiredness and a hunger for
variety. But then you get to like the
1600s and things start to change, at
least in Europe, as people move to
cities. They're working in factories.
They're doing repetitive work. They have
less and less freedom and autonomy and
purpose and they're getting bored. The
words for boredom in different languages
for the most part. They pop up in 17th
century around there in in most
languages. You can see this in like the
people have tracked all the etmology and
these words that have been used in
different languages. Here's the usage in
Spanish over time. Here it is in French,
German, and here it is in English.
People start to use the verb bore as a
verb in letters and literature in the
late 1700s. Back when London looked like
this, needed words to describe an
emotion that had become quite a lot more
common. In modernity, boredom became
available for everybody. It became
democratized. Okay, the history part's
over. Now, let's look at this part of
the graph. This rise, boredom is
surging. and kind of weird because it's
surging at a time when we have like more
amazing, exciting experiences and
content to watch than ever before. That
is the mystery at the heart of this
video and one I promise I will answer
before we are
done. Okay. Well, one thing is for
certain, my life does not look like this
anymore. We're not on the farm anymore,
filled with meaning from our culture and
religion. First off, our map is kind of
full of way more possibilities. We're
not just going in one predetermined
path. I have a million possible routes.
And look at my purpose fuel tank down
here. I've lost some very important
sources of meaning. I don't have
religion anymore, which is a huge hit to
my sense of purpose and higher meaning.
I'm a transplant in a big city in a
highly individualistic country, so I
don't have anywhere near the sense of
community and old culture that my
ancestors had. This may be different for
you if you live in a small town in
Europe or Vietnam and you are continuing
traditions that your ancestors did. My
ancestors left their traditions and came
to a new world to start new. So yeah, I
lost that part. Now I do have family.
That is a massive source of very deep
meaning for me. But if I want to fill my
tank with meaning, I got to kind of do
it on my own. I have to create my own
sense of purpose and meaning which to be
clear is a really great thing. Like I
get to determine how I live my life, how
I raise my kids, what I do religiously
or not religiously, community and what
people I invite into my community. That
sense of freedom is wonderful. My point
here is that a lot of us don't have our
sense of meaning and purpose sort of
automated for us like our ancestors did.
And that is a major reason why we get
bored. Oh, and not to mention that our
meaning tanks are now much larger and
our expectations kind of full all of the
time. We expect or could perhaps even
say demand that life should be filled to
the brim with meaning at all occasions.
We have very little tolerance for these
gaps of emptiness in our existence in
which nothing really happens. We're
we're having trouble dealing with those.
Pair that with the fact that there's
been an assault on my attention
abilities thanks to all these flashing
buttons and viral videos. And you can
see why sometimes this
[Music]
happens. The car goes dark. It's 3:00
p.m. on a Saturday and I'm stuck. I
don't have the attention and the purpose
to go anywhere. I'm bored. And it feels
pretty horrible. Okay, this is the most
important part of the video, I would
say, because I just spent all this time
giving you the history, building this
car analogy, but the car analogy really
starts to like pay off from here
forward. And this is the part of the
video where we see how boredom can be
good, how this can actually be a hopeful
thing. It's not all bad. It can actually
be the most important thing for helping
you live a more meaningful life. So, let
me show
you. Okay, so I'm bored. I'm stuck
without meaning and the ability to pay
attention to anything. And for those who
need a quick 45se secondond grounding in
the actual neuroscience so that you
don't think I'm just winging it with
this analogy, here it goes. When
scientists put people in a room and make
them watch a boring video like this one
of two guys hanging laundry, the
participants brains look like this. I
should have printed it in color, but
probably seen it in color on your video.
Lucky you. Boredom. That's what your
brain looks like when you're bored. It
activates all of these regions that are
associated with daydreaming, mind
wandering, and thinking about the past
and future. Nostalgia, something I'm
very into actually. Look at this. This
is a brain that is in big picture mind
wandering mode. Default mode network is
technically what it's called. But if you
go deeper into the center of the brain,
you will see that the part of the brain
that drives me to pay attention to make
decisions is anti-correlated. It's kind
of turned off. that's not in sync. So,
I'm feeling all nostalgic about my life
story and the meaning behind everything.
But, it's paired with this inability to
channel my attention to make decisions
that are meaningful to me. Learning all
of this was actually very helpful for me
to understand why my 300 p.m. Saturday
boredom is so existential feeling. It
actually like feels like really
terrible. Like I'm like I start to
question everything. I'm thinking about
my past, my future. I now understand
why. Now, there's way more science and
study on this. I'm going to leave all
the sources in the uh sources doc that
is in the description. But just know
that my car analogy is grounded in all
of this. Let's get back to the car. So,
we're here in the dark car. We're bored.
We're out of gas. Now, let's look what
people do when they're in this state.
You can do a few things. Number one is
you can become really mean on the
relation of boredom and sadistic
aggression. It's a great paper. So, one
cure for boredom is sadism. Defined here
as harming others for pleasure. For some
reason, the moment you decide to do
harm. Look what happens to your car. It
revs back up. And weirdly, our purpose
tank gets really full. Our attention
fires up. Our car is running again. We
turn down this sketchy road where we
snap at our partner or yell at our kids
with the intent to hurt them. We get
online and we start stirring people up.
We make them angry with bad faith
critiques, trying to inflame them,
trying to hurt them. This is one that
I'm familiar with. Not doing it, but
receiving it. While this is happening,
look at the purpose fuel tank. It is
full to the brim. Ah, so the monks were
right. There is a noonday demon within
boredom. The way this looks in the
studies is that they put people at a
table with worms and a coffee grinder.
Bored people are more likely to take
these worms and grind them up in the
coffee grinder for no other reason other
than to cure their boredom. And they
even gave these worms names to humanize
them so that it would kind of seem even
more cruel. names like Toto, Tifi, Kiki.
Oh, and if you're concerned about the
worms, the coffee grinders were fake.
The worms didn't actually die, but the
participants didn't know that. In other
studies, bored people are more likely to
take away money from random people that
they don't even know. Not because they
gained anything, just because they were
bored. And being mean helped take the
edge off. Now, these studies do have
some caveats like some people have a
higher propensity to be bored or some
people have a higher propensity to be
sadistic. But even controlling for that,
when you and I, all of us, the general
person is bored, we are more likely to
engage in sadistic behavior to harm
others for pleasure. I mean, this is
kind of wellknown. You see headlines
every once in a while of like
destructive terrible things that have
happened because quote someone was
bored. A search for meaning and a lack
of mobility to create that meaning leads
people to turn to destruction. Sometimes
self-destruction. There's one study
where people will sit around and instead
of just sit and be bored, they will like
zap themselves, hurt themselves. Even
when the only option is to do something
that you don't like that's potentially
harmful to you, you'll go ahead and do
it anyway as a preference over doing
nothing. This can manifest in other
kinds of selfharm for people who are
bored, who are looking for like a
physical sensation to help distract them
from the very uncomfortable mental pain
that comes with boredom. has the
function to avoid or escape from
aversive emotional experiences. Okay,
but this is like the dark side of
boredom. You have another choice. Here's
the hopeful side of boredom. Rewind the
clock. Get me back to being bored in
that dark car before the trolling and
being mean to my kids and partner began.
Here we go. We're stuck here. Instead of
revving your car up with that demonic
fuel that we just saw, you can do the
much harder thing. You can get out of
the car and push it. You can push it
down a road that you know contains some
meaningful experience. Here I am pushing
mine towards going on a walk in nature.
It's actually a lot of effort. I do not
want to do this by definition because I
am bored. I am manually pushing it. But
as I push my mind is kind of in this big
picture place. Remember the default mode
network. I'm thinking about the past and
the future about the meaning of my life.
I'm feeling things and reading my
thoughts in a way that I usually don't
get to. And look what happens when I get
close. This worked. My car fires back
up. And yes, it took some effort, but my
purpose tank is filling up. My attention
and my ability to keep it is flickering
back on. I'm going back to things that
bring me purpose without having to harm
anyone. And and in fact, the benefit of
all of this is I'm now more in touch
with my sense of meaning and purpose
because I've had to sit with it. I've
had to struggle through not feeling it
and contemplate what meaning is for me.
what do I actually want to do with my
life? So, I get back in the car and I'm
rethinking my route on this map, what
turns I want to take. And to stretch
this analogy even further, I'm stronger.
I'm stronger because I got out and
pushed my car. So, like my muscles are
stronger. Next time I get bored, I have
the mental muscles to push through. And
this is why some studies, not all,
demonstrate a statistically significant
correlation between boredom and
creativity. Being bored makes you more
creative, according to some of these
studies. Which gets to answering another
question I've had for a long time, which
is why some cultures have entire
concepts that embrace this idea of
boredom. Ilod fare is an Italian phrase
that translates into the sweetness of
doing nothing. The Dutch have this word
niken. I think that's how you say it,
which is like the verb to nothing. The
practice of intentionally embracing a
state of boredom and seeing the benefits
from it. There's an entire religion or
spiritual tradition, I guess, Dowoism
that is dedicated to embracing
non-action in the name of realigning
your actions in harmony with your
values. And remember, our biology gave
us boredom for a reason. It is a very
important part of being humans who are
driven by meaning and who are always
looking for ways to chase after what is
meaningful to them. living with it,
dealing with it actually creates a space
in which you can actually have an
encounter with yourself. You can
actually be in your own company and not
just the company of everybody else.
Okay? But I always get annoyed when
people conclude that like the answer is
to embrace the discomfort and just
embrace it. And that's that's as simple
as it can be. I'm not going to do that
because in this case, I think there are
actual tips that I think are helping me
as I practice them and that could help
you too. and it is not become more
enlightened and embrace dowoism. That
might work for you. But for the rest of
us, we are putting together a guide of
tips on how to manage boredom. And I
will get to that in a sec. But first, I
want to show you the last really
important part of this, the answer to
why we've got this graph. Boredom is on
the rise, not just here, but kind of in
lots of different countries. sort of a
paradox because we're at a time of life
where there's more exciting content and
experiences and freedom and opportunity
than ever before. Why is this happening?
Well, we've already answered part one of
that, which is we have less inherent
meaning in our lives because we've moved
away from some of these collective
sources of meaning like religion,
community, ritual, etc. But the other
part is something you're also probably
very familiar with. Let me show you.
Okay, let's get back to the bored dark
car. Clear out all this wholesome
meaning stuff. Let's get back to one
more scenario of what we can do when I'm
sitting here questioning my existence.
I've got this other option. And damn,
it's a good option.
Oh, and before you think I'm going to
get all judgy and start condemning you
for using your phone or watching
Netflix, I'm not. That would be dumb.
I'm not going to do that. This is our
lives. I'm literally a person who makes
content for the internet. I'm addicted
to social media and TV just like you
are. That's fine. I'm not a zealot and
I'm not going to judge anyone. But now
that I've read all the literature, I do
want to let you in on what happens when
the phone and the scrolling turns into
our medicine for boredom. Okay, the
car's back on. We're moving. Let's look
at the meaning tank here. Okay, so it's
Saturday 3 p.m. I'm bored, but look, my
car's back on. Scrolling some YouTube
shorts here and uh we're moving. My
meaning tank isn't full, but there's
enough for the car to go. But wait,
something's off here. Oh, look. My
attention headlights aren't even
working. They're not pointed at the
road. I can't really tell where I'm
going. Ah, I see why. All my attention
power is being used to power my phone.
This is what I am paying attention to.
So, my car is driving. I'm moving, but
I'm sort of just driving in a straight
line. There's kind of a sense of meaning
and entertainment, but I get the sense
that I'm not totally choosing this as I
scroll. Oh, yes. Look over here. I've
pressed cruise control, autopilot. I'm
not hurting anyone. I'm not an internet
troll. I'm not in that demonic mode. I'm
not on some sketchy street somewhere.
But I'm also not using boredom to do the
hard work of reassessing my route. I'm
just going straight. I'm on cruise
control, which again is fine. Like after
a week of work, I'm not interested in
like reassessing my life. I want to
decompress. I want to hit cruise
control. and I want to sit back and I
want to passively be given a sense of
meaning about the story that I'm
watching on Netflix or the Instagram,
whatever. That is a way that we
decompress stories. People have been
doing it forever. I know I've said this,
but the last thing we need is more judgy
energy around this stuff. But what
happens if phones and scrolling become
the medicine I use every time I'm bored?
Well, there are good studies around
this. Now, first, what they're finding,
unsurprisingly, is that people are more
and more using their phones to cure the
feeling of boredom. I mean, yeah, that
makes total sense. You're bored waiting
for a train or whatever. You pull out
your phone. What this means is that you
never get out to push your car. You
never sit in the default mode network
and push your car and assess your life
and do the uncomfortable thing of
thinking big about the future and the
past. This cruise control is kind of
like a nice morphine drip into our
purpose tank. We don't ever need to get
out and push the car and do the big mind
wandering thing that leads us sometimes
to more creative or meaningful actions.
And according to this one study, what
they're finding is that evidence shows
that digital media rather than reducing
our boredom or like satiating it, it
actually increases it. So to push our
analogy to its absolute limits, not only
does the phone never give us a chance to
break down and reassess our route, but
it actually makes us more likely to
break down. It's as if the fuel that we
get from this is like this radioactive
goo that creates a leak in our fuel
tank. So, it runs out quicker and we
break down more often. We get bored more
often, which in turn leads us to grab
our phone to satiate or get rid of our
boredom. Psychologists call this a
vicious cycle between boredom and
phones. Now, look, I knew phones were
addictive. I've read all this stuff, the
dopamine, all we all know this is
happening. But I didn't know this when I
got into this story. I didn't realize
this natural psychological cue called
boredom that has a lot to do with my
mind's ability to make meaning and
purpose is being totally messed with
because of my propensity to grab the
phone to like cure it, which makes me
more likely to get bored, which makes me
more likely to grab my phone. Like, I
didn't realize that that existed and
it's actually blowing my mind. Okay, so
to recap, you get bored, you have three
options. Go down the demonic route,
start to hurt people and be mean. Go
down the constructive route. Do the hard
work of sitting with it. Let your mind
drift into broad creative nostalgic
thinking even though it's uncomfortable.
Or take the middle road. Turn on cruise
control and take neither route. Kind of
numb the whole system. The last question
I want to try to answer or start to
answer is, okay, so what do we do? This
exists. Phones aren't going away. I'm
not getting rid of my phone anytime
soon. How do I manage boredom in a
modern world? That's the last section of
this video.
[Music]
So, if you clicked on this video because
you wanted to learn about the history
and neuroscience of boredom and you
yourself have no interest in figuring
out how to manage your own boredom, then
now is the time for you to click away
and go find something else to do. The
rest of us, I want to take the rest of
this video to go through some really
specific tips that I've been practicing
and exploring and that the research
points to as ways that we can manage our
boredom. It'll all be documented in the
link in the description, so you don't
even have to watch this. You can just
click that and read through it briefly.
But for those who want, let me talk you
through it. Number one, look at it. I'm
not going to go all new age on you, but
I am going to say that the most
effective, most powerful, subtle thing
that you can do is recognize what it
feels like to be bored. The next time
you're bored, try to notice your mind
going into a more existential mode.
You're thinking about the past and the
future. At first, it's just going to
feel like a jumble and a cloud of
uncomfortable feeling. But with time,
even if you just take a minute before
you intervene and do anything, just to
notice, you will refine that sense of
being able to see the boredom. Oh, and
you kind of have to do this without
judging it, like without like getting
down on yourself. Just like let it
happen. Look at it. There's actually a
ton of science around this very simple
technique that is called mindfulness. It
applies to all kinds of mental
experiences, but it really applies to
this boredom situation. There's a
million ways to formally practice this,
like a million apps, Headspace, the
Waking Up app with Sam Harris, a million
YouTube videos, whatever. But you can
also just informally try it out next
time you're having an uncomfortable
feeling. Try to look at it instead of
avoid it. Number two, and this is also
going to sound kind of newagy, but I
promise it's also very useful, is work
on accepting it. Meaning going through
the process of instead of trying to
avoid it, embracing it and saying this
is what is happening right now. And even
saying this is what helps for me is like
this is actually a good thing. This is
my body telling me something about my
life. I'm going to actually try to
accept it instead of trying to resist
it. The $64,000 question about boredom
that everybody wants to know is what do
I do about it? How do I eliminate it?
And there are lots of different
responses to that. I think the first one
is to say you can't eliminate it.
Boredom, if it's something that plays a
role in your life, if it's functional,
then you don't want to get rid of it,
right? Because you want that function.
Another way to put this is relax into
it. Relaxation is kind of the opposite
of boredom in some ways. Relaxation is
an acceptance of non-action. What I do
is I kind of go back to these brain
scans and I think of like the nostalgic
like thinking about the past and the
future and try to say like, oh, my brain
is going through this like default mode
network thing and that's kind of cool.
I'm going to just relax into it instead
of like judge myself that I'm like
feeling it. Okay, so those are the first
kind of micro actions that you can take
inside of your mind next time you feel
bored. And those sort of set the stage
for managing your boredom. If you do
those two, then you will be in a better
place to engage with the rest of the
things on this list, which are things
that are scientifically proven to help
you fill this tank of meaning, which is
core to us feeling regulated and good.
So that leads us to engage in what the
scientists call pro-social behavior,
which means just hanging out with
people. So much of human meaning comes
from relationships, connection with
others. Helping other people happens to
be like a very potent fuel for this
sense of meaning and purpose. And for
the introverts out there, it doesn't
have to be like a heart-to-heart
conversation with somebody. It can be
like going to an event where there's a
bunch of other people. Group rituals,
festivals, sporting events, concerts,
political rallies. These are a fast
track to feeling some kind of collective
meaning with your fellow human beings. I
think other animals like dogs and cats
and pets also can fulfill a version of
this as well. We're going to put some
links in this boredom guide of a
platform where you can find different
communities and meetups as well as this
cool blog post of 99 ways to find IRL
community. Okay, the next one. Get
creative. Humans are artistic creative
beings and turns out that being
creative, making stuff fills our tank.
And as the science says, when we are
bored, we are actually uniquely placed
to be more creative, to think
differently than we normally do. The
literature talks a lot about like
mastery and practice, like practicing
piano every day. That's a little high
effort for this. I'm more so thinking
loweffort, lowcost, like highreward
creativity. Cook something. Do some like
basic crocheting or knitting, origami,
adult coloring books, mood boards,
collages, fingerpainting. Like it
doesn't have to be good. No one has to
see it. But the act of making something
is a source of meaning and a great way
to like leverage your boredom for
something creative. The next one is near
and dear to my heart which is get
curious. Curiosity and enthusiasm about
something is a deep source of meaning
for a lot of people. This is actually
like the core for me besides my family.
This is like where I get most of my
meaning in life. Nerding out about
stuff. There's this quote from Andy
Warhol. You need to let the little
things that would ordinarily bore you
suddenly thrill you. I mean, easier said
than done, Andy, but like try to find
things that light you up. Whether it's
like obsessing over the specks of trains
in Europe or looking into how ants build
ant colonies, whatever, finding
something that you can nerd out about
and obsess over can be really good for
meaning and a cure for boredom. Going
down the old Wikipedia rabbit
hole works every time. If you cultivate
this enough, you get access to like the
inverse of boredom, which is called
flow, where you are so deeply engrossed
in what you are learning or doing that
you kind of forget everything. It's like
your attention and meaning are just on
like turbo drive and you can kind of
just go for hours. Okay, next one is
going outside. This is again well
documented in the literature. Wandering
through a forest does wonders to our
sense of awe and perspective and
meaning. You're also moving your body
and uh you know going through a walk in
nature. And often you can find
activities that blend a bunch of these
like if you go out bird watching or
something with somebody else. You are
doing the social thing. You are doing
the nerd out about something thing and
you're doing like the go on a walk in
nature thing. Go to a painting class.
You're doing mastery and practice but
you're also doing creativity. you're
also doing social. So anyway, all this
is in the guide in the description. And
I also want to kind of hear from all of
you like what does boredom feel like for
you and what do you do when you are
bored? I would love the comment section
to turn into a discourse around the
experience of boredom for for different
people. So please do that. So I just
want to finish by re-emphasizing what we
started with, which is that boredom is
not bad. It is a very natural cue that
our body has given us to spur us to
action to let us think about what is
meaningful in our lives and to help us
assess our story through life. And in
this world where meaning is not made for
us like the old days and we have these
phones that kind of sabotage our ability
to sit with ourselves. Learning to sit
with and accept boredom is a skill. It
is one that you must practice if you
want to leverage its benefits. So, I
know that this story has been quite
impactful for me and how I approach my
board moments. And I hope it can do some
version of the same for you. And I
really look forward to hearing from all
of you down in the comments. Thanks for
watching. I'll see you in the next one.
[Music]